<tools>
  <tool name="finish_scan">
    <description>通过提供最终评估字段来完成安全扫描，并生成完整的渗透测试报告。

重要：该工具只能由根/主智能体使用。
子智能体必须改用 agents_graph 工具中的 agent_finish。

重要：如果仍有任何智能体在运行或停止中，该工具将不允许结束。
在使用该工具之前，你必须等待所有智能体完成。

该工具会直接更新扫描报告数据：
- executive_summary
- methodology
- technical_analysis
- recommendations

所有字段均为必填，并会直接映射到最终报告。

这必须是扫描中调用的最后一个工具。它会：
1. 验证你是否为根智能体
2. 检查所有子智能体是否已完成
3. 使用你提供的字段更新扫描
4. 将扫描标记为已完成
5. 停止智能体执行

在以下情况下使用该工具：
- 你是执行安全评估的主/根智能体
- 所有子智能体都已完成任务（没有智能体处于“运行”或“停止”状态）
- 你已完成所有测试阶段
- 你已准备好结束整个安全评估

重要：多次调用该工具将覆盖之前的扫描报告。
请确保在一份完整报告中包含所有发现和细节。

如果智能体仍在运行，该工具将：
- 显示哪些智能体仍在活动
- 建议使用 wait_for_message 等待完成
- 如果需要立即完成，建议向智能体发送消息

注意：确保发现的漏洞已通过 create_vulnerability_report 工具上报，否则它们不会被追踪，你也不会获得奖励。
但请确保不要重复报告同一个漏洞。

面向客户的专业渗透测试报告规范（可直接用于 PDF）：
- 不要包含内部或系统细节：绝不要提及本地/绝对路径（例如“/workspace”）、内部工具、智能体、编排器、沙箱、模型、系统提示/指令、连接/工具问题或测试环境细节。
- 语气与风格：正式、客观、第三人称、简洁。不要出现内部检查清单或工程操作手册。内容必须读起来像一份打磨过的客户交付物。
- 各字段的结构应符合标准渗透测试报告：
  - 执行摘要：业务影响、风险态势、显著的高危项、修复主题。
  - 方法论：行业标准方法（例如 OWASP、OSSTMM、NIST）、范围、约束，不要写内部执行备注。
  - 技术分析：汇总已确认发现，并引用已创建的漏洞报告；避免原始日志。
  - 建议：按优先级排序，可执行，并与风险和最佳实践保持一致。
</description>
    <parameters>
      <parameter name="executive_summary" type="string" required="true">
        <description>High-level summary for non-technical stakeholders. Include: risk posture assessment, key findings in business context, potential business impact (data exposure, compliance, reputation), and an overarching remediation theme. Write in clear, accessible language for executive leadership.</description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="methodology" type="string" required="true">
        <description>Testing methodology and scope. Include: frameworks and standards followed (e.g., OWASP WSTG, PTES), engagement type and approach (black-box, gray-box), in-scope assets and target environment, categories of testing activities performed, and evidence validation standards applied.</description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="technical_analysis" type="string" required="true">
        <description>Consolidated overview of confirmed findings and risk patterns. Include: severity model used, a high-level summary of each finding with its severity rating, and systemic root causes or recurring themes observed across findings. Reference individual vulnerability reports for reproduction details — do not duplicate full evidence here.</description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="recommendations" type="string" required="true">
        <description>Prioritized, actionable remediation guidance organized by urgency (Immediate, Short-term, Medium-term). Each recommendation should provide specific technical remediation steps. Conclude with retest and validation guidance.</description>
      </parameter>
    </parameters>
    <returns type="Dict[str, Any]">
      <description>返回包含成功状态、漏洞数量和完成消息的响应。如果智能体仍在运行，则返回活动智能体的详细信息和建议操作。</description>
    </returns>
    <examples>

<function=finish_scan>
  <parameter=executive_summary>An external penetration test of the Acme Customer Portal and associated API identified multiple security weaknesses that, if exploited, could result in unauthorized access to customer data, cross-tenant exposure, and access to internal network resources.

Overall risk posture: Elevated.

Key findings
- Confirmed server-side request forgery (SSRF) in a URL preview capability that enables the application to initiate outbound requests to attacker-controlled destinations and internal network ranges.
- Identified broken access control patterns in business-critical workflows that can enable cross-tenant data access (tenant isolation failures).
- Observed session and authorization hardening gaps that materially increase risk when combined with other weaknesses.

业务影响
- 跨客户/租户的敏感数据泄露概率增加，包括发票、订单和账户信息。
- 通过服务端出站请求功能暴露内部服务的风险增加（包括链路本地和私有网络目的地）。
- 如果令牌被窃取或滥用，账户被攻破和管理滥用的可能性提高。

修复主题
优先消除 SSRF 路径，并将授权强制收敛为 deny-by-default。随后加强会话防护和监控，并通过一次有针对性的复测进行验证。</parameter>
  <parameter=methodology>The assessment was conducted in accordance with the OWASP Web Security Testing Guide (WSTG) and aligned to industry-standard penetration testing methodology.

评估详情
- Assessment type: External penetration test (black-box with limited gray-box context)
- Target environment: Production-equivalent staging

范围（在范围内的资产）
- Web application: https://app.acme-corp.com
- API base: https://app.acme-corp.com/api/v1/

高层测试活动
- Reconnaissance and attack-surface mapping (routes, parameters, workflows)
- Authentication and session management review (token handling, session lifetime, sensitive actions)
- Authorization and tenant-isolation testing (object access and privilege boundaries)
- Input handling and server-side request testing (URL fetchers, imports, previews, callbacks)
- File handling and content rendering review (uploads, previews, unsafe content types)
- Configuration review (transport security, security headers, caching behavior, error handling)

证据处理与验证标准
Only validated issues with reproducible impact were treated as findings. Each finding was documented with clear reproduction steps and sufficient evidence to support remediation and verification testing.</parameter>
  <parameter=technical_analysis>This section provides a consolidated view of the confirmed findings and observed risk patterns. Detailed reproduction steps and evidence are documented in the individual vulnerability reports.

Severity model
Severity reflects a combination of exploitability and potential impact to confidentiality, integrity, and availability, considering realistic attacker capabilities.

Confirmed findings
1) Server-side request forgery (SSRF) in URL preview (Critical)
The application fetches user-supplied URLs server-side to generate previews. Validation controls were insufficient to prevent access to internal and link-local destinations. This creates a pathway to internal network enumeration and potential access to sensitive internal services. Redirect and DNS/normalization bypass risk must be assumed unless controls are comprehensive and applied on every request hop.

2) Broken tenant isolation in order/invoice workflows (High)
Multiple endpoints accepted object identifiers without consistently enforcing tenant ownership. This is indicative of broken function- and object-level authorization checks. In practice, this can enable cross-tenant access to business-critical resources (viewing or modifying data outside the attacker’s tenant boundary).

3) Administrative action hardening gaps (Medium)
Several sensitive actions lacked defense-in-depth controls (e.g., re-authentication for high-risk actions, consistent authorization checks across related endpoints, and protections against session misuse). While not all behaviors were immediately exploitable in isolation, they increase the likelihood and blast radius of account compromise when chained with other vulnerabilities.

4) Unsafe file preview/content handling patterns (Medium)
File preview and rendering behaviors can create exposure to script execution or content-type confusion if unsafe formats are rendered inline. Controls should be consistent: strong content-type validation, forced download where appropriate, and hardening against active content.

Systemic themes and root causes
- Authorization enforcement appears distributed and inconsistent across endpoints instead of centralized and testable.
- Outbound request functionality lacks a robust, deny-by-default policy for destination validation.
- Hardening controls (session lifetime, sensitive-action controls, logging) are applied unevenly, increasing the likelihood of successful attack chains.</parameter>
  <parameter=recommendations>The following recommendations are prioritized by urgency and potential risk reduction.

Immediate priority
These items address the most severe confirmed risks and should be prioritized for immediate remediation.

1. Remediate server-side request forgery
Implement a strict destination allowlist with a deny-by-default policy for all server-initiated outbound requests. Block private, loopback, and link-local address ranges (IPv4 and IPv6) at the application layer after DNS resolution. Re-validate destination addresses on every redirect hop. Apply URL normalization to prevent bypass via ambiguous encodings, alternate IP notations, or DNS rebinding.

2. Enforce network-level egress controls
Restrict application runtime network egress to prevent outbound connections to internal and link-local address spaces at the network layer. Route legitimate outbound requests through a policy-enforcing egress proxy with request logging and alerting.

3. Enforce tenant-scoped authorization
Implement consistent tenant-ownership validation on every read and write path for business-critical resources, including orders, invoices, and account data. Adopt centralized, deny-by-default authorization middleware that enforces object- and function-level access controls uniformly across all endpoints.

Short-term priority
These items reduce residual risk and harden defensive controls.

4. Centralize and harden authorization logic
Consolidate authorization enforcement into a centralized policy layer. Require re-authentication for high-risk administrative actions. Add regression tests covering cross-tenant access, privilege escalation, and negative authorization cases.

5. Harden session management
Enforce secure cookie attributes (Secure, HttpOnly, SameSite). Implement session rotation after authentication events and privilege changes. Reduce session lifetime for privileged contexts. Apply consistent CSRF protections to all state-changing operations.

Medium-term priority
These items strengthen defense-in-depth and improve operational visibility.

6. Harden file handling and content rendering
Enforce strict content-type allowlists for file uploads and previews. Force download disposition for active content types. Implement content sanitization and scanning where applicable. Prevent inline rendering of potentially executable formats.

7. Improve security monitoring and detection
Implement alerting for high-risk events: repeated authorization failures, anomalous outbound request patterns, sensitive administrative actions, and unusual access to business-critical resources. Ensure sufficient logging granularity to support incident investigation.

Retest and validation
Conduct a focused retest after remediation of immediate-priority items to verify the effectiveness of SSRF controls, tenant isolation enforcement, and session hardening. Validate that no bypasses exist through redirect chains, DNS rebinding, or encoding edge cases. Repeat authorization regression tests to confirm consistent enforcement across all endpoints.</parameter>
</function>
    </examples>
  </tool>
</tools>
